Guide to the IBT Rail Conference records, 1904-2016 IBT0069
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
IBT Rail Conference records
1904-2016
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
International Brotherhood of Teamsters
Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers and Trainmen
Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employees
IBT0069
2.5 Linear Feet
This collection houses IBT Rail Conference records collected by current IBT divisions and its historic predecessors. Materials include magazines, correspondence, newsclippings, notebooks, photos, and various by-laws and agreements related to railroad unions. Materials are dated from 1904 to 2016.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
These materials were transferred from the IBT in 2015.
Arrangement
Collection is organized in two series: Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers and Trainmen Division and Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employees Division.
Biographical / Historical
The Teamsters Rail Conference represents more than 70,000 rail employees in the United States who work as locomotive engineers, trainmen and maintenance of way workers on the five major freight railroads, Amtrak and numerous commuter rail systems and short lines. The Conference was formed in early 2004 after the merger of the Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers and added to in late 2004 when the Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employees also merged with the Teamsters.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists mainly of items produced by or relating to the predecessor organizations of the Teamsters Rail Conference: the Brotherhood of Locotomove Engineers and the Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employees.
Labor unions -- United States -- History -- 20th century; International Brotherhood of Teamsters; Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers and Trainmen; Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employees
- Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers and Trainmen Division, 1904-2013; Series 1
  Scope and Contents
  This series holds materials of the Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers, both before and after its official affiliation with the International Brotherhood of Teamsters. Materials include photos, journals, notebooks, and convention programs. Materials are dated from 1904 to 2013.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged by item or document type.
  - "Souvenir-Sixth Biennial Convention of the Grand Botherhood of Locomotive Engineers and G.I.A.", May 11, 1904; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers Journal Vol. 34, No.12, December, 1905; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Beneficial Association of Providence Division, No. 35 of the O.R.T., 1914; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letter to the General Chairman of the Legislative Board, 1924; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Locomotive Engineers Journal, Vol. 64, No. 10, October, 1930; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Photo: "Officers of the Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers meet in Detroit to discuss Jubilee-seated L to r-R.E. Bigelow, V.J. Feth, Paul M. Smith, and JJ Roach", February 2, 1938; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Timebook and Ft. Wayne Div. Roster-B. of L.E., 1944; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Constitution, By-Laws, and Rules Governing the Sick Accident and Funeral Department of A.G. Porter Lodge No. 141", 1945; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "A Century of Service" Souvenir Program-BLE Centennial/GIA Diamond Jubilee -Detroit, MI, May 5-8, 1963; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Directory-Divisions, General Committee of Adjustment and Legislative Boards and Officers, Trustees and Branches of the Locomotive Engineers Mutual Life & Accident Insurance Association, March, 1972; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "C.E. Leafgreen" Timebook and News clips, 1974; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - By-Laws-Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers & Trainmen, 2006-2010; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - PowerPoint Slides-"How the BLET PAC Works: Legislative Representative Workshop", May, 2010; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Locomotive Engineers & Trainmen News, October/November, 2010; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "The History of the BLET", 2013; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Journal of the Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers, 1891 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Arbitration Award and Vacation Agreement, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Hebdin L. Smith Photograph - Grand Trunk Western 60 Year Locomotive Engineer, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Guide for Secretary Treasurers of Local Unions, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Division Legislative Representative, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - BLET News / Journal, 2007-2010 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Division LR Workshop - Regulatory Writing, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - LEARN Conference Materials, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Member Mobilization Legislative Workshop, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Legislative Representative Training Class, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Locomotive Engineers and Trainmen News, 2011 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - 150th Anniversary Keychain, 2013 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - 150th Anniversary Card, 2013 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous Clippings and Photographs, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - High Alert Newsletters, ND (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Welcome to the Teamsters Rail Conference, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Resolution of the Advisory Board, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - 7th International Convention Women's Auxiliary Badge, 1906; IBT 0069 Series 1 (Box Shared Box 34, Folder 2)
  - Amtrak: An American Story, 2011; Series 1 (Box Shared Box 36, Folder 24)
- Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employes Division, 1920-2016; Series 2
  This series holds materials of the Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employees, both before and after its official affiliation with the International Brotherhood of Teamsters. Materials include photos, journals, notebooks, and convention programs. Materials are dated from 1920 to 2016.
  This series is araanged by item or document type.
  - Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employes Division Journal-"Golden Jubilee Year 1887-1937" Vol.XLVI, No.6, June, 1937; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - "Certificate of Loyal Membership" Dining Car Employees Union -Joseph Turner, June 22, 1950; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Teamster Members-Welcome to the Teamsters, 2005; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - BMWED Journal, Vol. 114-123, 2005-2014; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - By-Laws Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employes Division, 2006; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Bylaws-Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employes Division, 2010; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Second National Convention Proceedings-Grand Sierra Resort, Reno, Nevada, October 4-7, 2010; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Railroad Labor Board Photograph and Ebay Invoice, 1920 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - "Burlington Route" Rules and Rates of Pay for Locomotive Engineers and Agreement with the General Committee of Adjustment, 1923-1946 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Time Magazine Ad and Union Pacific Railroad Leaflet, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Rail Conference Agreements, 1941-1954 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Boston and Albany Railroad Company Stock Certificate for Laura Brooks, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Railway Carmen's Journal, Vol. LXIX No. 8, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Railway Employees Journal, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - BMWED Journals, 2016 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Outline of Major Changes in New Book of Rules, ND (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Unlabeled Photographs and Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employees Division Sticker (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - BMWE Journals, 1920-1947 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Agreements, 1942-1951 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Operating Department Rules and Instructions (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Photographs, ND (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs, ND (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employes Journal Vol. II, 1893 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - The President's Report, Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employes, 37th Regular Convention, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 3)